[Music]
so good so we can finally get underway uh so
this is uh CS 6700 reinforcement learning if
anyone is here by mistake looking for the
planning class still should leave okay and
um yeah so so how many of you were in the
machine learning course just for me to get a
sense okay large fraction of
the people were enl okay and
uh so this is uh a very uh uh a different
kind of learning than what we looked at it
uh ml right so uh so in machine learning we
looked at familiar modes of machine learning
where the idea was to learn from data you know
so you had given a lot of data as training uh
instances for you and essentially you were
trying to learn from those training instances
as to what to do right and there were different
kinds of problems that we are looking at so one
was supervised learning problem in which uh
we looking at classification and regression
yeah so in the machine learning class we looked
at learning from data right primarily so one of
the um models we looked at was supervised learning
right where we learned about classification and
regression uh the goal there was to learn an
in mapping from an input space to a uh output
which could be a categorical output in which case
it's classification could be a continuous output
in which case it was called regression right
so if you haven't been in the ML Class don't
worry about it right because this is just to
tell you that RL is not whatever you learned
in the ML Class okay so if you have haven't
learned anything in the ML Class then you
don't have anything to unlearn so don't worry
so the second part second kind of learning uh
thing we looked at was unsupervised learning
uh where there was really no output that was
expected of you right since therefore there was
no supervision uh the goal was to find patterns
in the input data I'll give you a lot of data
points you can find out if there are groupings
of you know similar kinds of data points can I
divide them into segments right so that kind of
thing was called clustering right or you are
asked to figure out if there were frequently
repeating patterns in the data right and so
this is called frequent pattern mining or
derived problem there was Association rule Mining
and so on so forth right so people have heard me
give this analogy multiple multiple times before
but this is the most apt one how did you learn to
cycle right so was it superwise learning
so how did you learn to cycle somebody who
hasn't heard me or who hasn't been in ml you
haven't been in ml right yeah okay how did
you learn to cycle was did somebody tell you
how to cycle and then you just follow their
instruction okay first of all do you know how to
cycle yes do you know how to cycle yeah you yes
yes okay how did you learn to cycle down fell
down a couple of times and that automatically
made cycle you have you have to actually
figure out how to not to fall down right
so falling down alone is not enough but you have
to try different things right it's not supervised
learning right it's really not supervised learning
how much ever you think because now that I have
given this uh talk multiple times people are
getting Vice to it right earlier when I used
to ask this people used to say of course it's
supervised learning my uncle was there holding
me or my father was telling me what to do and so
on so forth right at best what did they tell you
hey look out look out don't fall down right
so that doesn't count as supervision right so
or keep your body right keep your body up or
some some kind of very vague instructions was
what they giving you right supervised learning
would mean that so you get on the cycle somebody
tells you okay now push down with your left foot
with three lounds of pressure right and move your
center of gravity 3° to the right right so this
is I mean somebody has to give you exactly what
is the the the control signals that you have to
give to your body in order for you to cycle right
then that would be supervised learning right if
some somebody actually gives you supervision at
that scale you probably have never learned to
cycle if you think about it right because it's
such a complex complex uh dynamical system if
somebody gives you control at that level gives
you input at that level you never learn to cycle
and so immediately people flipped and say that
it was unsupervised learning right because yeah
of course nobody told me how to cycle therefore
it's unsupervised learning so if it is truly
unsupervised learning what should happened is
you should have watched uh hundreds of videos of
people cycling figured out what is the pattern of
cycling that they do okay and get on a cycle and
reproduce it right so that is essentially what
unsupervised learning would be you just have lot
of data right and based on the data you figure out
what the patterns are and then you try to execute
those patterns that doesn't work right you can
watch hours and hours of uh somebody playing
fight simulator you can't go and fly a plane
right so so you have to get on the cycle
yourself and you have to try things yourself
right so that's that's the Crux here right so what
it's it's how do you learn to cycle is neither
of the above right it's neither supervised nor
unsupervised it's a it's a different Paradigm so
the reason I always start out uh my uh talks not
just in the class but in general when I talk about
reinforcement learning is because uh people always
talk about reinforcement learning as unsupervised
learning right which always really irks me because
it's not unsupervised learning just because you
don't have a uh classification error or or a class
label doesn't make it unsupervised learning it's a
it's completely different form of learning and
so reinforcement learning is essentially this
mathematical formula for this trial and error kind
of learning right so how do you learn from this
kind of minimal feedback you know falling down
hurts or somebody your your mom or somebody stands
there and claps when you finally manage to get get
on the cycle you know that's kind of a positive
reinforcement right they fall down you get hurt
right that's kind of a negative feedback how do
you just use this kinds of uh minimal feedback
and you learn to cycle so this is essentially
the the Crux of what reinforcement learning is
about Trail and error right uh so the goal here
is to learn about a system through interacting
with the system right it's not something that is
done completely offline okay you have some
notion of interaction with the system okay
and you learn about the system through that
interaction uh reinforcement learning originally
was inspired by uh behavioral psychology
right so one of the earliest reinforcement
systems that was studied was a Pavlov's dog
how many of you know of the Pavlov's dog
experiment what is a pao's dog
experiment and Pao he tried to
give food to dog and whenever he
gave food dog it started salivating
mhm and a b in association with whenever he's
going to give food to them okay so whenever like
he just started ringing the bell the dog started
expecting the food and it started uhhuh so that
is called a condition refle so when the dog looks
at the food and it starts salivating right it's a
Primary Response because there is a reason for
it to salivate on the site of food any idea why
exactly so it's preparing to digest the food you
know mean show the food it's preparing to digest
the food so it starts salivating right so then
now if you think about it right hearing the bell
and it elevates what is it doing preparing to
digest the Bell so when you ring the bell and
then serve the food the dog forms an association
between the the Bell and the food right and later
on when you just ring the bell without even
serving the food the dog starts salivating in
response to digesting the food that it expects
to be delivered right so essentially the food
is the payoff you know the food is like a reward
for it and it has learned to form associations
between signals in this case which was the Bell
like an input signal which was the Bell and the
reward that is going to get right so this is
called uh behavioral conditioning right and
uh so inspired by these kinds of experiments on
more complex behavioral experiments on animals
and people started to come up with different
theories to explain how learning proceeds right
in fact some of the earlier uh reinforcement
learning papers uh appeared in behavioral
psychology journals right the earliest paper by
Satan BTO um appeared in brain and Behavioral
Sciences Journal just just go back uh I needed to
need to say something about s b know that there's
a larger audience we can tell that about them
so the we have we're going to follow a textbook
written by Rich and Andy BTO right uh but uh
more importantly they are also kind of the
co-founders of the modern field of reinforcement
learning right so in 1983 they wrote a a paper
uh um um adaptive neuron like element that learn
control Behavior or some something to the effect
right and that essentially kickstarted this
whole modern field of reinforcement learning
so the concept of reinforcement learning like I
said goes back to Pavo and earlier right people
have been talking about this kind of Behavioral
conditioning and learning and stuff uh but um
uh the whole modern uh computational uh techniques
that people use in reinforcement
learning are started by uh certain and
right so what is reinforcement learning right so
it's learning about stimuli right the inputs that
are coming to you and the actions that you can
take in response to it right learning about the
stimuli only from rewards and punish punishments
okay so you're not going to get anything else food
is a reward right falling down and scraping your
hand is a punishment right so only from this kinds
of rewards and punishments alone right there is
no detailed supervision available nobody tells
you what is the response that you should give to
a specific input right suppose you are playing a
game there are multiple ways in which you can
learn to play a game right so you can learn to
play chess by looking at a board position right
and then looking at a table right that tells you
for this board position this is the move you have
to make right and then you go and make the move
right so so that is a kind of supervision that
you could get you know that gives you a kind
of a mapping from the input to the output right it
gives you mapping from the input to the output and
um essentially you learn to generalize from that
so this is what we mean by detailed supervision
so another way of learning to play chess is you
just okay you have an opponent you sit in front
of him and you just make a sequence of moves
at the end of the move you win okay you get
a reward right somebody pays you say 10 Rupees
okay if you lose you have to pay the opponent
10 Rupees that's all that's all that happens
right that's all the feedback you're going to
get right whether you're going to get the 10
rupees or going to lose the 10 Rupees at the
end of the game so nobody tells you given this
position this is the move you should have made
right that's what we mean by saying learning from
rewards and punishments in the absence of detailed
supervision okay is it clear okay and The crucial
component to this is Trail and error learning
because since I don't know what is the right
thing to do given an input right I need to try
multiple things to see what the outcome will
be right I need to try different things to see
if I'm going to get the reward or not right if I
don't try different things right I'm not going to
be able to learn anything at all right so we'll
I can give you more formal mathematical reasons
for why we need all of this as we go go on uh but
this intuitively you can understand this as uh uh
requiring uh uh EX exploration so that you know
what the right outcome is right and there are a
bunch of things uh which are also characteristic
of reinforcement learning problems one of those
is uh that uh the outcomes right the pay the
the rewards and punishments based on which you
are learning can be fairly delayed in time they
need not be temporarily close to the thing that
cost it I mean while you're playing a game
let us say right so you might uh you know
or drop a batsman right and then he goes on
to score like 150 or something like that right
so then you lose the match at the end of the
day right but the even that cost you to lose
the match is the dropped catch that probably
happened around the 12th over right or it could
be a much more convoluted uh causal uh cause
and effect right so and how many of you follow
Cricket my god really losing popularity yeah put
your hand I'm not going to give a cricket example
then look at it uh okay so there a bunch of other
things right so so we talked about delayed rewards
the rewards could come much later in time from the
action that caused the reward to happen right for
example let's go back to our cycling case right
I might have done something stupid on or I might
have gone over a stone somewhere right while I'm
cycling at a very high speed there might have been
a small Stone in the the road and that that will
cause me to lose my balance right and then I'll
try my level best to get the balance back right
I might not and I'll finally fall down and get
hurt that doesn't mean what costed the Falling
Down is the Last Action I tried right I might
have desperately tried to jump off the cycle or
something like that but that is not what cost the
punishment right what caus the punishment happened
a few few seconds ago when I ran over the stone
right so there could be this kind of a temporal
disconnect between what causes the reward or
punishment from the actual reward and Punishment
so it becomes a little tricky how do you going
to learn those things right learn the associations
right so quite often right you are going to need a
sequence of actions to obtain a reward right it's
not going to be like a onot thing you're going to
need a sequence of actions to get to the reward so
again going back to the chess example right you're
not going to get a reward every time you move
a piece on the board right you have to finish
playing the game at the end of the game if you
actually manage to win you get a reward so it's
a sequence of actions right and therefore you need
to learn some kind of an association between the
inputs that you are seeing in this case it will
be both positions right or how fast the cycle is
moving and how unbalanced do you feel and so on
so forth right two actions so the inputs that you
are getting sometimes which we call States right
and and the actions that you take in response to
this input that you are seeing right so this
is essentially what you're going to be doing
when you're solving a a reinforcement learning
problem so this kind of of associations are
essentially known as policies right so what you're
are essentially learning is a policy to behave in
a world right so you're learning a policy to play
chess or you're learning a policy to cycle right
so this is essentially what you're learning that
you're not just learning about individual actions
right and all of this happen typically in a noisy
stochastic World okay that makes makes things
more challenging so these are all the different
characteristics of uh uh reinforcement learning
problems right and um and we'll be looking at all
of this as we go along right I mean this I'll not
be explicitly talking about each and every one
of these bullet points but everything that we
look at all the algorithms all the methods that
we look at as we go along in this course okay
we'll we'll have all all these aspects as part
of it okay uh so reinforcement learning has been
used fairly successfully in in a wide variety of
applications right uh so you can see a helicopter
there okay so there not a cut and paste error
okay the helicopter is actually flying upside
down okay uh so uh so the this um group group at
Stanford and Berkeley uh which have actually used
reinforcement learning to train a helicopter to
fly uh all kinds of things not just upside down
a naral agent can do all kinds of tricks on the
helicopter so I'll show you a video in a minute uh
and uh it's it's an amazing piece of work right I
mean it's considered uh it was considered the the
showpiece application for reinforcement learning
I mean getting such a complex control system uh to
work and it actually could do things at a much
uh finer levels of control than a human being
could right well that's after all a machine so you
would expect that but the tricky part was how it
learned to control this complex system uh from uh
without any human uh intervention right and in the
middle right so I have a couple of games there
so that is uh can you see that okay it's twoo
small and arrow yeah that's a game called back
gamon right so how many of you know about back
gamon one two there was one
maybe how many of you know about
Ludo okay fine so back gaming is like a two-player
Ludo okay so you throw the dice you move pieces
around and you take them off the board right
so it's it's it's it's a fairly U easy game
but then you have all kinds of strategies that you
could do with it but it's also a hard game for uh
computers to play because of the stochasticity
right and also because of a large uh branching
factor that is there in the game right so at each
point there are many many combinations in which
you could move the uh board pieces around
and then there is this D roll that adds an
additional complexity so people aren't really uh
you know getting great results and then there's
this person Jerry tessaro from IBM uh who um came
up with something called neurog gamon I think it
was called neurog gamon and uh that was trained
using supervised learning under neural network
right and so if it if he had done it recently it
would have been called a deep learning version
of neurog gammer or something because he did it
back in the '90s early '90s it was just called
neural network version of back gam and it it it
played really well for a computer program right
so it was essentially the best computer program
back gamman player at that point and then uh
Jerry heard about uh uh TD I mean heard about
reinforcement learning and he decided to train
a reinforcement learning agent to play bam okay so
what he did was uh set up this uh um reinforcement
learning agent which played against another copy
of itself right and let them play hundreds and
hundreds of games right rather thousands and
thousands of games so essentially what they
did was so you train one copy for like 100 100
move 100 games or something then you move it
here right freeze it and then continue learning
with this so essentially what was happening as
you learn you're playing against better and
better plays gradually your opponent was also
improving right and then this was called selfplay
right so he trained back gam using selfplay
and uh he it came to a point where the the TD gam
as he called it was even better than the human
player of bamon at that point in the world right
so they actually had a head-to-head challenge with
the human Champion that is a world championship of
back gamman you know it's apparently very popular
in the Middle East and people actually have World
Championships that's the world championship of
B gamman and uh so he he challenged the human
Champion which IBM seems to do a lot right I mean
they challenge casparo uh to matches and things
like this so he also challenged uh uh justar
worked for IBM you should realize right people who
spend a lot of resources getting computers to play
games will probably be working for IBM you know
uh so so so Jerry had this thing and it beat the
world world champion so you have reinforcement
learning uh agent that's the best back gaming
player in the world okay not not no more best
computer player or anything right so we could
actually make that claim right and there's another
game there which is a snapshot from the game of
go right so people have played go oh come on us
there at least one or two people who have played
go okay uh people have played U
otelo okay that's also very number I
mean isn't it one of those free games on
Ubuntu I thought everybody plays that because I
mean at some point or other well you would rather
play Oto than watch paint Dr you know but anyway
so go goes like a more more complex version of AO
F right it's it's it's again a very hard game
for uh computers to play because the branching
factor is huge right and it is actually a miracle
that humans even play this uh because the the
search trees and other things are really complex
right so this is one uh one case which clearly
illustrates that humans actually solve problems
in a fundamentally different way than we try to
write down in our algorithms because we seem to
be making all kinds of intuitive leaps in order
to be able to play go right so there's this
person uh David silver uh who currently works
for Google Deep Mind and uh but before that he
spent some time with uh Jen tesaro at IBM and at
some point along the way he came up with this uh
reinforcement learning agent called uh TD search
uh that play go at a decent level still not um you
know not not like Master human level performance
but it perform plays at a pretty decent level
right so what I'm pointing out here is things
that are typically hard for traditional computer
algorithms or even traditional machine learning
approaches to solve AI has had good success
right and here is another example oh if I'm
to point I'm supposed to use this or that I forget
which one right they told me I should use only one
of those screens for pointing because it's hard
for them to record on another one I forget which
one okay forget it there are some robots
on the bottom left of the screen right and
uh so that's a snapshot from uh the UT Austin
Robo soccer team called Austin Villa right uh
and they use reinforcement learning to get their
robots to execute really complex strategies so so
that's it's it's really cool uh but the nice thing
about the uh the robo soer application is that uh
they don't use reinforcement learning alone right
they actually use a mix of uh different learning
strategies and also planning and so on so forth
which is going on the other studio right so they
use a mix of different kinds of AI and machine
learning techniques in order to get a very very
competent agent it's very hard hard to beat and
they have been the Champions I think for like 2
or 3 years running now uh in the humanoid league
right and again hard control problems uh things
like uh how do I take a spot kick you know those
are the things for which they use reinforcement
learning which it's a really hard balancing
problem you basically have to balance the
robot on one leg and then swing the other leg
so that you can take the kick it turns out to
be a hard control problem right so they they
used RL to RL to solve those right and then
up on the top right okay uh is is is an
application which will probably the one
that actually makes money uh of all these
three all all the others right uh that is on
uh essentially on um using reinforcement
learning to solve online learning right
so so online learning is is is is a is a use case
where uh I do not get I don't have the feedback
available to me a priori right so the feedback
keeps coming peace meal right so for example uh
that is a case where uh we are having uh new
stories that need to be shown to people that
come to my web page right and when people come uh
come to the page I'll have like some editors will
pick like 20 stories for me and from those 20
stories I have to figure out which are the ones
I put up there prominently right and what is the
feedback I'm going to to again nobody tells me
what stories that user is going to like I mean
I cannot have a supervised learning algorithm
here right so the feedback I'm going to get is
if the user clicks on the story I'm going to get
a reward the user does not click on the story I
will not get a reward right that's essentially
the feedback I'm going to get nobody tells me
anything beforehand right so I have to try out
things I have to show different stories to figure
out which one he's going to click on right and I
have very few attempts to do this in so how do
I do this more effectively so people have done
a supervised approach for solving this and it has
worked fairly uh successfully uh so it has worked
fairly successfully but um but reinforcement
learning seems to be a much more uh uh you know
natural way of modeling these problems so not
only in these kinds of uh news story selection
people use reinforcement learning ideas even in
ad selection right so how do you see some of those
ads that you see on the sides when you go to
Google or some other page right so how how are
those ads selected so so there might be some very
basic economic Criterion for selecting a slate
of ads okay here are these 10 ads which would
probably give me the right uh payoff right and
then you can figure out which of those which
three of those 10 am I going to put here and
things like that you could use a reinforcement
learning solution for uh selecting those right of
course the this there's this whole field called
computational advertising right it's a lot more
complex than what I explained uh but uh RL is is
a component in computational advertising as well
right okay here is the video courtesy Andrew's
web page uh the people recognize a guy there yeah
okay it's just not a human siiz
helicopter but still it's a fairly large
amazing huh all of this is being learned by uh our
agent this goes on for a while so we'll stop
[Music] [Applause]